Wartime Military Experiences 1992 ohrc081
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Wartime Military Experiences
1992
Center for Documentary Research and Practice
Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory
ohrc081
12 Interviews Audio files, transcripts, and collateral materials
This project consists of interviews with war veterans. Interviewees discuss their war and military experiences. World War I through the Vietnam War are covered in this project. The interviews include discussions of military food, shelter, weapons, and travel.
Scope and Content Note
This collection contains twelve interviews conducted in August of 1992. The interviews range from nineteen to seventy-one minutes. All interviews consist of audio tapes but are not transcibed.
Acquisition Information
Oral history interviews conducted by the Indiana University Center for the Study of History and Memory from 1968 to the present, with particular focus on the history of twentieth-century America and the Midwest.
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-021; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 27 minutes
  Access Status
  Restricted: Contact center staff for more information
  Scope and Content Note
  Anonymous, born July 30, 1933, discusses his experience in the navy during the Korean War through 1956. He served on the USS Princeton and the USS Orka. He discusses ship life, accidental deaths, and racial discrimination. He also discusses the end of the war.
  engineer; Hong Kong; Korea; Philippines; accidental deaths; African American sailors; Communism; Korean War; racial discrimination; ship life; shore patrol; USS Orka; USS Princeton; United States. Navy
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-023; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 20 minutes
  Anonymous, born November 24, 1921, describes his experiences in the military during World War II. He discusses racial discrimination, military life, and the barracks.
  New Guinea; Philippines; barracks; military draft; military food; military life; Pacific Theater; racial discrimination; ship life; V-J Day; World War II; United States. Navy
- Evans, Maurice, August, 1992; 92-022; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 2 tapes, 1 7/8 ips, 71 minutes; newspaper articles about interviewee
  Restricted: Contact the Center for Documentary Research and Practice for more information.
  Maurice W. Evans, born January 24, 1894, discusses his experience as an African American in the army during World War I. He discusses basic training, travel to France, and his duties while in France as a member of a supply company. He also discusses military life, barracks, food and homecoming. He discusses racial discrimination in the army that he witnessed and experienced.
  Barber; minister; Bloomington, Indiana; France; New Port News, Virginia; Paoli, Indiana; Spencer, Indiana; St. Nazaire, France; 1918 Armistice; African-American soldiers; barracks; basic training; military food; military life; military supplies; prisoners of war; racial discrimination; ship life; USS George Washington; veterans; World War I; 308th Supply Company; American Red Cross; Showers Brothers Furniture Company; United States Army; Blair, Jim; Keener, Edgar; Wilson, Woodrow
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-029; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 22 minutes
  Anonymous, born 1916, discusses his experiences in the army during World War II. He describes his most memorable experiences, military food, shelter, and combat.
  engineer; Cheyenne, Wyoming; Germany; bivouac; combat; military training; postwar employment; war souvenirs; wartime casualties; World War II; United States Army
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-019; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 25 minutes
  Anonymous, born March 8, 1933, discusses his experiences in the military during the Korean War. He explains why he joined the service and his voyage to Korea. He also discusses combat, military life, and racial discrimination.
  Indianapolis, Indiana; Korea; African-American soldiers; combat; infantry; Korean War; military food; military training; racial discrimination; ship life
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-028; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 25 minutes
  Anonymous discusses his experience as a soldier in Vietnam. He discusses combat, food, and housing of war. He also describes the North Vietnamese and Viet Cong. He describes discrimination against African-American troops and the negative public response to all the soldiers that fought in Vietnam.
  engineer; Cambodia; Fort Dix, New Jersey; Fort Waynewright, Alaska; Mekong, Vietnam; Saigon, Vietnam; Tokyo, Japan; bivouac; C-rations; combat; drug use; military food; military integration; military training; military uniforms; North Vietnamese; prisoners of war; racial discrimination; service medals; support troops; Tet Offensive; Viet Cong; Vietnam War, 1961-1975; Vietnam War protests; wartime casualties; weapons; United States Army Reserves
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-025; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 37 minutes
  Anonymous, born December 2, 1917, discusses being in the United States Navy during World War II. He describes the USS York, training, his work, and his illnesses.
  Guantanamo Bay, Cuba; Tuskegee, Alabama; African-American troops; military training; ship life; supply company; USS New York; war souvenirs; weapons; World War II; United States. Navy
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-026; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 19 minutes
  Anonymous, born October 3, 1919, discusses serving in the 96th Special Battalion of the United States Army during World War II. He discusses the work that he did, his travels with the military and the living conditions. He talks about the lack of celebration at his return after the war, and he also talks about his career as a truck driver.
  stevedore; truck driver; 96th Special Battalion; homecoming; military training; military travels; stevedoring; World War II; United States. Navy; United States Navy SeaBees
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-027; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 34 minutes
  Anonymous, born 1911, discusses his experience in the military during World War II. He discusses the training of African-American troops in San Antonio, Texas. He describes racial segregation and discrimination that he and others experienced. He also discusses his medical discharge and his return to Bloomington, Indiana.
  Bloomington, Indiana; San Antonio, Texas; 2nd Cavalry Division; 92nd Infantry Unit; African-American community; African-American troops; Ku Klux Klan; medical discharge; military draft; military training; physical education; racial discrimination; racial segregation; racism; railroad; recreation; World War II; Indiana University; United Service Organization; West Side Community Center
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-020; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 31 minutes
  Anonymous, born March 2, 1922 describes being drafted into the military during World War II. He explains his job as a military cook on the battlefront. He discusses being in Normandy on D-Day and his experience when his outfit was captured by enemy troops and he was not. He also describes seeing many German soldiers surrender to become prisoners of war. The interviewee then discusses returning to the United States.
  cook; farmer; truck driver; Belgium; Germany; African-American troops; battlefront; combat; D-Day; German troops; military draft; military food; military training; prisoners of war; war souvenirs; World War II
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-024; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape, 1 7/8 ips, 48 minutes
  Anonymous, born 1933, describes his experiences in the army from 1953-1955, while he was stationed in Korea. He discusses military daily life and his responsibilities as a tank driver and gunner. He also discusses being drafted at the same time that the military was integrating the troops. He discusses racial discrimination he experienced in basic training and when he requested a promotion.
  gunner; tank driver; Chicago, Illinois; Korea; 8th Bomber Division; Korean War; military draft; military food; military integration; military life; military rank; North Koreans; postwar life; racial discrimination; racial segregation; ship life; weapons; United States Army
- Anonymous, August, 1992; 92-030; Welch, Ted; Not transcribed; 1 tape 1 7/8 ips, 35 minutes
  Anonymous, born 1934, discusses his experience in the United States Marine Corps. He discusses training, the Korean War, and being stationed in Honolulu, Hawaii. He also describes military food, recreation, combat, weapons, and housing.
  Honolulu, Hawaii; Korea; bivouac; C-rations; combat; military food; military life; military supplies; military training; prisoners of war; racial discrimination; recreation; war souvenirs; weapons; United States Marine Corps